<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="1" system="local" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0 https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd">
  <dataset>
    <title>Interagency Ecological Program: Discrete water quality data from the Sacramento River floodplain and tidal slough, collected by the Yolo Bypass Fish Monitoring Program, 1998 - Present</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <surName>Interagency Ecological Program (IEP)</surName>
      </individualName>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Nicole</givenName>
        <surName>Kwan</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1178-7788</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Mallory</givenName>
        <surName>Bedwell</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9553-6032</userId>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Nicole</givenName>
        <surName>Kwan</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1178-7788</userId>
      <role>Creator, Associate, Data contact, Field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jesse</givenName>
        <surName>Adams</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0739-8782</userId>
      <role>Field crew</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <abstract>
      <para>
    The Yolo Bypass Fish Monitoring Program (YBFMP) operates a rotary
    screw trap and fyke trap and conducts biweekly beach seine and lower
    trophic surveys in addition to maintaining water quality
    instrumentation in the bypass. The YBFMP serves to fill information
    gaps regarding environmental conditions in the bypass that trigger
    migrations and enhanced survival and growth of native fishes, as
    well as provide data for IEP synthesis efforts. YBFMP staff also
    conduct analyses of YBFMP monitoring data to address pertinent
    management related questions as identified by IEP. The Yolo Bypass
    has been identified as a high restoration priority by the National
    Marine Fisheries Service and US Fish and Wildlife Service Biological
    Opinions for Delta Smelt, Winter and Spring-run Chinook salmon and
    by California EcoRestore. The YBFMP informs the restoration actions
    that are mandated or recommended in these plans and provides
    critical baseline data on the ecology of the bypass and how it
    interacts with the broader San Francisco Estuary. Only juvenile and
    adult fish catch with associated water quality are presented in this
    dataset. Our overall program objectives include:
  </para>
      <para>
    Specifically, the objectives of the water quality monitoring are to:
  </para>
      <para>
    We sample physical water quality discretely when conducting
    biological monitoring using a YSI ProDSS. Nutrient and chlorophyll
    data are taken biweekly along with lower trophic tows. Water is
    sampled at three sites along the Yolo Bypass and Sacramento River,
    then processed and analyzed by an internal DWR laboratory.
  </para>
    </abstract>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This information is released under the Creative Commons license - Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). The consumer of these data ('Data User' herein) is required to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use. The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available 'as is.' The Data User should be aware, however, that data are updated periodically, and it is the responsibility of the Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank you.</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Yolo Bypass tidal slough and seasonal floodplain in Sacramento, California, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-121.8074</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-121.5368</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>38.794</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>38.2347</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2011</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2022</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <taxonomicCoverage>
        <taxonomicClassification>
          <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
        </taxonomicClassification>
      </taxonomicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Nicole</givenName>
        <surName>Kwan</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1178-7788</userId>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Mallory</givenName>
        <surName>Bedwell</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9553-6032</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Water Quality&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Water quality parameters are recorded at the start of each sampling
    event. Water temperature (degrees Celsius), electrical conductivity
    (microSiemens/cm), specific conductance (microSiemens/cm), pH,
    dissolved oxygen (mg/L), and turbidity (FNU) are sampled with a YSI
    ProDSS handheld meter. Turbidity values are averaged over three
    readings. Secchi depth is measured in the shade. Light attenuation
    (subsurface irradiance) is measured with a light meter (LI-COR
    LI-250A) at the surface, and at 75%, 50%, 25%, and 1% of the surface
    reference value in the water. The corresponding depth and measured
    micromoles are noted. Tide, condition of sampling (condition code),
    Microcystis level, and weather are also recorded with water quality
    parameters. Please see the YBFMP SOP on Lower Trophic Sample
    Collection for more details. Water Collection and Filtration Water
    quality samples are collected using a van dorn. Collection bottles
    are rinsed three times with sample water before being filled and are
    stored in a cooler with ice while being transported to the
    laboratory for filtration. For each sample of chlorophyll a and
    pheophytin a, between 80-500 mL of sample water is passed through a
    47 mm diameter glass fiber filter with a 1.0 m pore size at a
    pressure of 10 inches of mercury. After filtration, the filters are
    immediately frozen and transported to DWR’s Bryte Laboratory for
    analysis within 48 hours of collection (Standard Methods, 19th
    edition).
  </para>
          <para>
    Orthophosphate (dissolved), dissolved nitrite + nitrate, dissolved
    organic nitrogen, dissolved calcium, dissolved chloride, total
    dissolved solids, and dissolved silica surface are filtered
    immediately after returning to the laboratory. The samples are
    filtered through a 0.45 µm pore size mixed cellulous ester membrane
    filter into one-pint polyethylene bottles, one of the bottles being
    an actual sample bottle turned into Bryte for analysis and the other
    being a designated filtration bottle which is rinsed between sites
    that are being filtered. The filtered water either remains in the
    one-pint sample bottle or is transferred from the designated
    filtration bottle to acidified half pint bottles (one with HNO3 and
    one with H2SO4). All waters samples are stored in the refrigerator
    and the chlorophyll filter samples are stored in the freezer. All
    samples are then transported to Bryte Laboratory within 48 hours for
    analysis.
  </para>
          <para>
    Dissolved organic carbon (DOC) samples are filtered using a metal
    DOC filtration system. The samples are filtered through a 45 µm pore
    size mixed cellulous ester membrane filter. A glass flask is triple
    rinsed with DI and then 20-30 mLs of sample water are filtered and
    used to rinse the flask three times. Water is then filtered and
    transferred to a 40 ml glass vial that is pre-preserved with
    phosphoric acid. Please see the YBFMP SOP on Lower Trophic Sample
    Collection for more details.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Sample Processing and Tracking&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Sample Tracking&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Samples are tracked using an internal system called FLIMS. A chain
    of custody (COC) listing sample number, date, time, location, and
    study/project is sent to Byte Labs, who check that all samples are
    accounted for and turned in at the correct temperature. Signatures
    are required of both the person responsible for dropping off the
    samples, and the person receiving it.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Contractor&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Since July 2009 (see historical changes for more information)
  </para>
          <para>
    DWR Bryte Labs
  </para>
          <para>
    1450 Riverbank Road
  </para>
          <para>
    West Sacramento, CA 95605
  </para>
          <para>
    916 376-1959
  </para>
          <para>
    https://water.ca.gov/Programs/Environmental-Services/Water-Quality-Monitoring-And-Assessment
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Quality Assurance and Control&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Instrument Specifications&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    All YSI ProDSS instrumentation is specified in the ProDSS Manual.
  </para>
          <para>
    All laboratory instrumentation is listed in the Bryte Lab Quality
    Manual.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Calibrations&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    YSIs are calibrated for Specific Conductance, pH, Dissolved Oxygen,
    and turbidity monthly. YSI temperature readings are verified twice
    per year: once using a 5-point validation and once using a 2-point
    validation. Please see the YBFMP SOP on ProDSS Calibration for more
    detail. Prior to sample analysis of conventional and inorganic
    constituents in water, external calibrations will be made using 3 -
    5 standards that cover the range of sample concentrations. The
    lowest standard will be at or near the Method Detection Limit (MDL).
    Linear regression will be &amp;lt;0.995 or better. Calibration
    verification will be run after every 20 samples after the initial
    calibration and will use a standard source that is different from
    that used for the initial calibration. Acceptable recovery for
    conventional analytes is 80 - 120% and for inorganic analytes is 90
    – 110%.
  </para>
          <para>
    See Bryte Chemical Laboratory Quality Manual for additional details.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Replicates/Duplicates/Blanks&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Equipment blanks - A blank is created for each day of sampling for a
    subset of nutrient samples, for a total of two equipment blanks. DI
    water is used to rinse sampling equipment, and then the equipment is
    filled with DI water and distributed for filtering or filling
    non-filtered bottles. Blanks are run for: dissolved ammonia,
    dissolved orthophosphate, dissolved nitrate + nitrate, total
    kjeldahl nitrogen, and total phosphorus. Replicates - A replicate
    chlorophyll sample is taken for each site. The same amount of sample
    water as the parent sample is filtered to create this replicate
    sample.
  </para>
          <para>
    Laboratory Control Samples – Laboratory control samples (LCS)
    provide bias information about a laboratory’s ability to perform
    acceptable analyses on a clean matrix with the chosen methods. The
    LCS will be prepared by the laboratory using an aliquot of the clean
    matrix (e.g., water, sediment, or tissue with no detectable levels
    of the target analytes) that is spiked with the analytes at known
    concentrations. The lab results must be within 80-120% recovery or
    control limits based on 3 times the standard deviation of a lab’s
    actual method recoveries for the target analytes to be acceptable.
  </para>
          <para>
    Matrix Spikes – Matrix Spikes (MS) provide bias information on
    sample preparation and analysis. MS will be used to verify that the
    lab can determine if the sample matrix is causing either a positive
    or negative bias on sample results. MS samples will be prepared by
    the laboratory using an aliquot of the sample matrix (e.g., water
    sediment, or tissue) that is spiked with the analytes at known
    concentrations. The lab results must be within 80-120% recovery or
    control limits based on 3 times the standard deviation of a lab’s
    actual method recoveries for the target analytes to be acceptable.
  </para>
          <para>
    Matrix Spike Duplicates – Matrix spike duplicates (MSD) provide
    precision information on sample preparation and analysis. The
    laboratory will prepare separate spiked matrix samples (MS) for
    analysis. Acceptable lab results for bias are the same as described
    for matrix spikes. The duplicate values must have a RPD of less than
    25% to be acceptable.
  </para>
          <para>
    Laboratory Duplicates – Laboratory duplicates provide precision
    information on the analytical methods with the target analytes. The
    laboratory will generate the duplicate samples by splitting one
    sample into two parts, each of which will be analyzed separately.
    The duplicate values must have an RPD of less than 25% to be
    acceptable.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Data Quality Control&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Three levels of quality control are conducted on field data:
  </para>
          <para>
    Field data are checked by someone other than the data recorder prior
    to leaving each field site
  </para>
          <para>
    Datasheets are checked while being entered into the Microsoft Access
    database, which has customized error-checking and data validation
    checks
  </para>
          <para>
    A separate DWR staff member compares data from original field sheets
    to data entered into the database
  </para>
          <para>
    DWR’s Field and Laboratory Information Management System (FLIMS) is
    used to track water quality field and lab data from collection in
    the field to final use and storage. Prior to each monthly water
    quality run, FLIMS is used to generate the paperwork (sample
    identification numbers, labels, chain of custody sheets, etc.) for
    each field run. The data collected in the field is recorded on field
    sheets and is typically entered into FLIMS the next day or before
    samples are submitted to Bryte Lab. Staff at Bryte Lab enters
    laboratory data directly in FLIMS that is uploaded to the Water Data
    Library (WDL) when all the data for one field day has been entered.
    If there is missing field and lab data, discrepancies between data
    on field sheets and WDL, or the data does not meet quality
    objectives, the Lower Tropic Lead is notified and corrections are
    made, or the data is flagged appropriately.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Notes on Data Quality: &lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Please see the historical changes section for changes in sampling
    methods.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Archiving&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    Samples are disposed of once analysis is complete.
  </para>
          <para>
    Data can be accessed on the Department of Water Resources Water Data
    Library: https://wdlbeta.water.ca.gov/Map.aspx
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Historical Changes&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Methods:&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    From May 2019 until November 2020: 0.45 µm MCE filters used for
    nutrient filtration (NO2+NO3, O-Phos, NH3, DON) were soaked in DI
    water for at least 4 hours before use. The water was changed after
    filters had soaked for an hour, and the hour soaking was repeated a
    total of 4 times.
  </para>
          <para>
    11/19/20: Bryte updated preservation methods for some constituents.
    TKN, TPhos, NO2+NO3, O-Phos, NH3, and DON were previously stored in
    unacidified half pint bottles and frozen. The new protocol is to add
    250 mLs of sample water into a bottle with H2SO4 and to store at
    5°C.
  </para>
          <para>
    June 2021- creation of the blank sample water was standardized.
    Previously a sample of DI from the lab faucet was filtered. Now the
    DI is passed through whichever sampling vessel was used (churn
    splitter or van dorn) and then added to a designated blank 1L
    Nalgene bottle.
  </para>
          <para>
    June 2021- the filter used to filter the DOC sampled changed from a
    combusted 1 µm glass fiber filter to a 0.45 µm MCE filter. Use of a
    glass filtering flask and a vacuum pump was also added to the DOC
    filtering protocol.
  </para>
          <para>
    October 2021- water grabs in the field are now standardized to use
    the van dorn in order to take a homogenized sample.
  </para>
          <para>&lt;emphasis role="strong"&gt;Methods References&lt;/emphasis&gt;</para>
          <para>
    AEU: DWR-6-SOP-024_v1.1_YSI ProDSSCalibration
  </para>
          <para>
    AEU/Bryte: DES-1-MNL-001Bryte Lab Quality Manual version 4.0
  </para>
          <para>
    AEU: DWR-6-SOP-015_v1.7_LowerTrophicSampleCollection
  </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Interagency Ecological Program: Discrete water quality data from the Sacramento River floodplain and tidal slough, collected by the Yolo Bypass Fish Monitoring Program, 1998 - Present</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Nicole</givenName>
          <surName>Kwan</surName>
        </individualName>
        <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
        <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1178-7788</userId>
        <role>Creator, Associate, Data contact, Field crew</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Jesse</givenName>
          <surName>Adams</surName>
        </individualName>
        <organizationName>California Department of Water Resources</organizationName>
        <electronicMailAddress>California Department of Water Resources</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0739-8782</userId>
        <role>Field crew</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>
        <para>State Water Project</para>
      </funding>
    </project>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
